<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>JACK Audio Connection Kit News</title>
    <link href="https://jackaudio.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <icon>https://jackaudio.org/assets/icons/favicon-32x32.png</icon>
    <link href="https://jackaudio.org"/>
    <updated>2021-10-13T17:35:30+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://jackaudio.org/</id>
    <entry>
        <title>Past, Present and Future of the JACK Audio Connection Kit (in video form)</title>
        <author><name>falkTX</name></author>
        <link href="https://jackaudio.org/jackaudio.github.com/news/2019/11/14/past-present-and-future-of-the-jack-audio-connection-kit-in-video-form/"/>
        <published>2019-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <id>/jackaudio.github.com/news/2019/11/14/past-present-and-future-of-the-jack-audio-connection-kit-in-video-form/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I did a talk/presentation at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sonoj.org/&quot;&gt;Sonoj&lt;/a&gt;,
regarding the past, present and future of the JACK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk was live-streamed and recorded, and now Sonoj videos are online,
so you can watch this at &lt;a href=&quot;https://media.ccc.de/v/sonoj2019-1902-jack-past-present-future&quot;&gt;https://media.ccc.de/v/sonoj2019-1902-jack-past-present-future&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>JACK2 v1.9.17 release</title>
        <author><name>falkTX</name></author>
        <link href="https://jackaudio.org/jackaudio.github.com/news/2021/01/15/jack2-v1.9.17-release/"/>
        <published>2021-01-15T17:13:13+00:00</published>
        <id>/jackaudio.github.com/news/2021/01/15/jack2-v1.9.17-release/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new version of JACK2 has just been released.&lt;br/&gt;
You can grab the latest release source code at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&lt;/a&gt; and macOS/Windows installers at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2-releases/releases&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2-releases/releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release focuses on improvements to the macOS and Windows binaries, now with macOS universal builds natively supporting Apple M1 hardware.&lt;br/&gt;
On M1 hardware, you can now have native arm64 JACK clients talk to Intel/x64 once and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Windows, JACK-Router (the special ASIO driver that allows any ASIO-compatible application to talk to other JACK clients)
has been brought back, now integrated with the installer so it is much easier to manage.&lt;br/&gt;
Also, 32-bit and 64-bit clients can now be mixed without any side-effects to the meta-data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please restart the JACK server after updating to 1.9.17 on those systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official changelog is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add jack-router to Windows installer, opt-in&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix jack_control stopping after first command iteration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix library compat/current version under macOS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix registry keys for Windows, add 32bit compat ones on 64bit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix return codes of jackd on success&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ignore DB_VERSION_MISMATCH error on windows, it is expected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove old workaround for asio4all, as it breaks with jack-router&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support for arm64 macOS builds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show welcome and license pages on windows installer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update QjackCtl used in macOS/Windows installers to v0.9.0, with some commits cherry-picked from develop branch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Website infrastructure changes</title>
        <author><name>falkTX</name></author>
        <link href="https://jackaudio.org/jackaudio.github.com/news/2019/11/19/website-infrastructure-changes/"/>
        <published>2019-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <id>/jackaudio.github.com/news/2019/11/19/website-infrastructure-changes/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The jackaudio Website changed its infrastructure from being self-hosted and generated by a script, to being built and hosted by GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main reason for this was to easily make the publishing of the static files automatic.
Although it is definitely possible to do this without GitHub, why waste time setting up something that already exists?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means changes made by a pull-request that get merged into master, will immediately be visible in the website, without anyone having to run scripts or click more buttons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that a fallback solution is in place in case something goes wrong with GitHub (which is basically going back to what we had before).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, the way to create posts (like these) has changed. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jackaudio.github.com/blob/master/README.md&quot;&gt;README&lt;/a&gt; for the website has more details.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>macOS and Windows nightly builds</title>
        <author><name>falkTX</name></author>
        <link href="https://jackaudio.org/jackaudio.github.com/news/2021/08/13/macos-and-windows-nightly-builds/"/>
        <published>2021-08-13T16:21:54+00:00</published>
        <id>/jackaudio.github.com/news/2021/08/13/macos-and-windows-nightly-builds/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just a small heads up to mention that macOS and Windows nightly builds are now available for JACK2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find them in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/actions&quot;&gt;JACK2 GitHub actions&lt;/a&gt; section, each successful build will have matching artifacts.&lt;br /&gt;
When you open a pull request, builds will be automatically generated.&lt;br /&gt;
(pending approval from JACK2 maintainers, but there is typically no reason not to approve)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These artifacts include macOS-intel, macOS-universal, Ubuntu 20.04, Windows 32bit and Windows 64bit builds.&lt;br /&gt;
Note that neither QjackCtl or JACK-Router are included in these builds, only JACK.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>JACK2 v1.9.16 quick hot-fix (for v1.9.15)</title>
        <author><name>falkTX</name></author>
        <link href="https://jackaudio.org/jackaudio.github.com/news/2020/10/16/jack2-v1.9.16-quick-hot-fix-for-v1.9.15/"/>
        <published>2020-10-16T19:22:53+00:00</published>
        <id>/jackaudio.github.com/news/2020/10/16/jack2-v1.9.16-quick-hot-fix-for-v1.9.15/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;An issue was found on the last JACK2 release that caused a few applications to crash on start.&lt;br/&gt;
This is a quick hot-fix for that release. If you are running v1.9.15, please update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of a new release being needed, we took the chance to remove the jack-router Windows code,
as it now belongs &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack-router&quot;&gt;in its own repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br/&gt;
These two items are the full release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can grab the latest release source code at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also grab the latest pre-built installers for macOS and Windows at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2-releases/releases&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2-releases/releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br/&gt;
On other systems, ask your jack2 package maintainer to update to the latest release.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>JACK2 v1.9.19 release</title>
        <author><name>falkTX</name></author>
        <link href="https://jackaudio.org/jackaudio.github.com/news/2021/07/16/jack2-v1.9.19-release/"/>
        <published>2021-07-16T13:41:07+00:00</published>
        <id>/jackaudio.github.com/news/2021/07/16/jack2-v1.9.19-release/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new version of JACK2 has just been released.&lt;br/&gt;
You can grab the latest release source code at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&lt;/a&gt; and macOS/Windows installers at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2-releases/releases&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2-releases/releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release focuses on 2 main things: &lt;code&gt;jack_position_t::tick_double&lt;/code&gt; addition and forced alignment of a few internal data structures.
A few other fixes were made as contributed by developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This relase adds &lt;code&gt;tick_double&lt;/code&gt; to the &lt;code&gt;jack_position_t&lt;/code&gt; struct and &lt;code&gt;JackTickDouble&lt;/code&gt; as a validation flag for it.
Since older versions of JACK do not expose this variable, the macro &lt;code&gt;JACK_TICK_DOUBLE&lt;/code&gt; is provided, which can be used as build-time detection.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alignment change is because the packed structure layouts as used in JACK2 need to be naturally aligned in order to be accessed atomically in some systems.
A non-aligned read or write can result in a &amp;quot;Bus error&amp;quot;, which brings down jackd.
This seems to only be relevant on certain ARM systems, as JACK2 was obviously working before this change for most people.&lt;br/&gt;
As a consequence of this change, the internal protocol version was bumped to 9, which &lt;b&gt;requires the restart of the JACK server&lt;/b&gt; after the update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official changelog is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add jack_position_t::tick_double, and flags around it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add zalsa &amp;quot;-w&amp;quot; argument to wait for soundcard to be available&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bump internal protocol version to 9 (due to struct alignment)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix alignment of fields for atomic accesses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix build for platforms needing __STDC_FORMAT_MACROS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix compilation of documentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;External changes, related to macOS/Windows installer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix macOS microphone permissions on qjackctl macOS app bundle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update qjackctl to 0.9.4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, for the rationale behind the transport &lt;code&gt;tick_double&lt;/code&gt; API update:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When using JACK transport to sync between clients with precise timing requirements (such as MIDI sequencers) rounding errors would accumulate and eventually make the separate clients out of sync.&lt;br/&gt;
This was observed in Carla and mod-host, which use audio plugins as JACK clients.
Some MIDI plugins could miss notes due to rounding errors.
This change has been deployed in MOD Devices for a couple of releases already and it is known to work (that is, it corrects the situation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were discussions on IRC about this potentially be unnecessary, that clients can just use &lt;code&gt;bar_start_tick&lt;/code&gt; to store the non-integer part of the tick.&lt;br/&gt;
While the idea could work in theory, supporting it turns out to be non-trivial and from all applications that I have tested none implemented this part correctly.&lt;br/&gt;
Some applications do not set &lt;code&gt;bar_start_tick&lt;/code&gt; at all, even though they can be run as transport master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So since the transport API has padding members available for use and it has been unchanged for several years (so there won&#039;t be a need to add more fields in the short or middle term), well let&#039;s just go for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is example code for transport-listening clients:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;hljs language-cpp&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hljs-keyword&quot;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; tick;
&lt;span class=&quot;hljs-meta&quot;&gt;#&lt;span class=&quot;hljs-meta-keyword&quot;&gt;ifdef&lt;/span&gt; JACK_TICK_DOUBLE&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;hljs-keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (pos.valid &amp;amp; JackTickDouble)
    tick = pos.tick_double;
&lt;span class=&quot;hljs-keyword&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;
#endif
    tick = pos.tick;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Meta-data pages restored</title>
        <author><name>falkTX</name></author>
        <link href="https://jackaudio.org/jackaudio.github.com/news/2019/10/12/meta-data-pages-restored/"/>
        <published>2019-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <id>/jackaudio.github.com/news/2019/10/12/meta-data-pages-restored/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just a small heads up to mention that meta-data related pages
like &lt;a href=&quot;https://jackaudio.org/metadata&quot;&gt;https://jackaudio.org/metadata&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://jackaudio.org/metadata/pretty-name&quot;&gt;https://jackaudio.org/metadata/pretty-name&lt;/a&gt;
have now been restored.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>JACK2 v1.9.12 release and future plans</title>
        <author><name>falkTX</name></author>
        <link href="https://jackaudio.org/jackaudio.github.com/news/2017/12/21/jack2-v1.9.12-release-and-future-plans/"/>
        <published>2017-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <id>/jackaudio.github.com/news/2017/12/21/jack2-v1.9.12-release-and-future-plans/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few days ago a new version of JACK2 was released.&lt;br/&gt;
You can grab the latest release source code at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br/&gt;
The official changelog is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix Windows build issues&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix build with gcc 7&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show hint when DBus device reservation fails&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add support for internal session files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you did not know already, I am now maintaining JACK2 (and also JACK1).&lt;br/&gt;
So this latest release was brought to you by yours truly. ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The release was actually already tagged on the git repo quite some time ago,
but I was waiting to see if Windows builds were possible.&lt;br/&gt;
I got side-tracked with other things and 1.9.12 ended up not being released for
some time, until someone reminded me of it again... :)&lt;br/&gt;
There are still no updated macOS or Windows builds, but I did not want to delay
the release further because of it.&lt;br/&gt;
The 1.9.11 release (without RC label) was skipped to avoid confusion with the
versions.&lt;br/&gt;
So 1.9.12 is the latest release as of today. macOS and Windows binaries still
use an older 1.9.11 version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being the maintainer of both JACK1 and JACK2 means I can (more or less)
decide the future of JACK.&lt;br/&gt;
I believe a lot of people are interested to know the current plan.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, JACK1 is in bug-fix mode only.&lt;br/&gt;
I want to keep it as the go-to reference implementation of JACK,
but not add any new features to it.&lt;br/&gt;
The reason for this is to try to get JACK1 and JACK2
to share as much code as possible.&lt;br/&gt;
Currently JACK2 includes its own copy of JACK headers, examples and utilities,
while JACK1 uses sub-repositories.&lt;br/&gt;
During the course of next year (that is, 2018) I want to get JACK2 to slowly use
the same stuff JACK1 does, then switch to use the same repositories
as submodules like JACK1 does.&lt;br/&gt;
This will reduce the differences between the 2 implementations, and make it
a lot easier to contribute to the examples and utilities provided by JACK.&lt;br/&gt;
(Not to mention the confusion caused by having utilities that work in simlar yet
different ways)&lt;br/&gt;
We will keep JACK1 &amp;quot;frozen&amp;quot; until this is all done.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, but not least important, is to get the JACK1 specific features into JACK2.&lt;br/&gt;
A few things were added into JACK1 after JACk2 was created,
that never made it into JACK2.&lt;br/&gt;
This includes meta-data (JACK2 does have the API, but a non-functional one)
and the new internal clients.&lt;br/&gt;
The purpose is to reduce reasons users might have to switch/decide between
JACK1 and JACK2.&lt;br/&gt;
JACK2 should have all features that JACK1 has, so that most users choose JACK2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, you are probably getting the impression that the focus will be on JACK2,
which is correct.&lt;br/&gt;
Though I realize some developers might prefer JACK1&#039;s design, the long &amp;quot;battle&amp;quot;
of JACK1 and JACK2 needs to stop.&lt;br/&gt;
Development of new features will happen in the JACK2 codebase,
and JACK1 will slowly become legacy.&lt;br/&gt;
Well, this is my personal plan at least.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not sure if this all can be done in 2018, but better to take things slowly
and get things done than do nothing at all.&lt;br/&gt;
I will keep you updated on the progress through-out the year.&lt;br/&gt;
Happy holidays everyone!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>JACK mailing list is back!</title>
        <author><name>falkTX</name></author>
        <link href="https://jackaudio.org/jackaudio.github.com/news/2019/12/16/jack-mailing-list-is-back/"/>
        <published>2019-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <id>/jackaudio.github.com/news/2019/12/16/jack-mailing-list-is-back/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The mailing list for the JACK Audio project is back!
You can now find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://lists.linuxaudio.org/listinfo/jackaudio&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The archive was restored, but not the subscriber list (due to technical difficulties).
You will have to re-subscribe in order to keep using the JACK mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>JACK-Session has been marked as deprecated</title>
        <author><name>falkTX</name></author>
        <link href="https://jackaudio.org/jackaudio.github.com/news/2020/07/16/jack-session-has-been-marked-as-deprecated/"/>
        <published>2020-07-16T12:01:11+00:00</published>
        <id>/jackaudio.github.com/news/2020/07/16/jack-session-has-been-marked-as-deprecated/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A small heads-up for developers, JACK-Session API has now officially been marked as deprecated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been working together with other members of linuxaudio community to get a better session-management API out there.
We previously had difficulties with this due to issues regarding the upstream project.
It was obvious to us that the NSM API is superior to all others that came before it (thanks to the initial hard work of its author, Jonathan),
but working with upstream has proven immensely difficult or even impossible..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of a few weeks ago, a few members of the linuxaudio group decided to fork the original NSM project and make a new one.
The acronym remains, so we still call it &amp;quot;NSM&amp;quot;, but the new project is now &amp;quot;New Session Manager&amp;quot; while the original is &amp;quot;Non Session Manager&amp;quot;.
We are working together with the community to make this session-management API and tools the best as they can be.
(The original was a bit lacking on the user-experience side of things..)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find more about the &amp;quot;New Session Manager&amp;quot; project &lt;a href=&quot;https://linuxaudio.github.io/new-session-manager/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
This includes links to the source code, bug/issue tracker and documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please give it a look, or better, a chance.
For now it is specific to POSIX systems like Linux and BSD, but it can be extended in the future.
If we manage to make (Audio) Session Management really work in Linux, that is already a big step up from other tools/APIs that came before it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We recommend all JACK application developers to implement NSM in their software.
Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>JACK2 v1.9.18 release</title>
        <author><name>falkTX</name></author>
        <link href="https://jackaudio.org/jackaudio.github.com/news/2021/04/15/jack2-v1.9.18-release/"/>
        <published>2021-04-15T12:36:24+00:00</published>
        <id>/jackaudio.github.com/news/2021/04/15/jack2-v1.9.18-release/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new version of JACK2 has just been released.&lt;br/&gt;
You can grab the latest release source code at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&lt;/a&gt; and macOS/Windows installers at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2-releases/releases&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2-releases/releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release focuses on 2 main things: adding zalsa internal client and fixing macOS builds in regards to DB/meta-data.&lt;br/&gt;
A few other fixes were made as contributed by developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With zalsa now part of JACK2, we are one more step closer to JACK1 feature parity.&lt;br/&gt;
Worth noting that this is purely the client, we still need to add the switches to be able to load internal clients directly from &lt;code&gt;jackd&lt;/code&gt; startup command-line.&lt;br/&gt;
Will be interesting to attempt to make this zalsa client also behave as a &amp;quot;slave adapter&amp;quot; like done with ALSA &lt;code&gt;audioadapter&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;coremidi&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;winmme&lt;/code&gt; drivers.&lt;br/&gt;
Something for a future release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On macOS, please restart the JACK server after updating to 1.9.18.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official changelog is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add zalsa_in/out as internal client (based on zita-a2j/j2a and jack1 code)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix jack_midi_dump deadlock on close after the jack server is restarted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix interrupt signal for linux futex waits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix usage of meta-data in official macOS builds (private DB errors)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Log error message when cleaning previous DB (macOS and Windows)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now for those unaware of this whole &amp;quot;zalsa&amp;quot; thing...&lt;br/&gt;
This is basically zita-a2j/j2a by Fons Adriaensen repackaged as an internal client instead of being an external standalone tool.&lt;br/&gt;
JACK1 already added this a few years ago.&lt;br/&gt;
This zalsa version is slightly more up to date and with a few new fixes on top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On supported systems, we can use it by running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;jack_load zalsa_out -i &quot;-d hw:Mio&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will activate the &amp;quot;Mio&amp;quot; soundcard as an output in the JACK graph.&lt;br/&gt;
You can use &lt;code&gt;jack_unload zalsa_out&lt;/code&gt; to deactivate it, or alternatively control the start/stop purely in CLI with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;jack_load -w -a zalsa_out -i &quot;-d hw:Mio&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which will automatically unload the internal client after Ctrl+C or SIGTERM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worth noting that, since internal clients run in the JACK server process,
they will log/print information on that process and not on the &lt;code&gt;jack_load&lt;/code&gt; one.&lt;br/&gt;
So watch out for that if you need to debug anything.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>JACK2 v1.9.14 release</title>
        <author><name>falkTX</name></author>
        <link href="https://jackaudio.org/jackaudio.github.com/news/2019/11/19/jack2-v1.9.14-release/"/>
        <published>2019-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <id>/jackaudio.github.com/news/2019/11/19/jack2-v1.9.14-release/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new version of JACK2 has just been released.&lt;br/&gt;
You can grab the latest release source code at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official changelog is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix ARM build&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix mixed mode build when meta-data is enabled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix blocking DBus device reservation, so it plays nice with others (like PipeWire)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use python3 for the waf build scripts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release is mainly for the mixed mode and DBus device reservation fixes.&lt;br/&gt;
A few distributions need those, and since not everyone is happy taking &amp;quot;random&amp;quot; git commits, a proper release is needed.&lt;br/&gt;
So there you go - a new release. :)&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>JACK2 v1.9.15 release and current status</title>
        <author><name>falkTX</name></author>
        <link href="https://jackaudio.org/jackaudio.github.com/news/2020/10/15/jack2-v1.9.15-release-and-current-status/"/>
        <published>2020-10-15T12:29:50+00:00</published>
        <id>/jackaudio.github.com/news/2020/10/15/jack2-v1.9.15-release-and-current-status/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new version of JACK2 has just been released.&lt;br/&gt;
You can grab the latest release source code at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This version of JACK2 brings back binary builds for macOS and Windows.&lt;br/&gt;
You can grab the latest pre-built installers at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2-releases/releases&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2-releases/releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few notes about the new installers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is the author&#039;s first time on doing such installers, there might be some small oddities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have old JACK2 installations on macOS or Windows, please uninstall those first (they are not 100% compatible)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JackRouter is not included, as it does not work on macOS 10.15 and can be problematic on Windows.&lt;br /&gt;
New maintainers welcome! Existing code moved to separate &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack-router&quot;&gt;jack-router&lt;/a&gt; repository.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;macOS 11 (the new arm64 &amp;quot;apple-sillicon&amp;quot;) is not supported at the moment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Report any issues to jack2 repository (the jack2-releases repository is for automated builds only)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official changelog is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automated builds for macOS and Windows (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2-releases&quot;&gt;jackaudio/jack2-releases&lt;/a&gt; repository)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adapt wscript Windows build configuration to match old v1.9.11 installer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bump maximum default number of clients and ports (now 256 clients and 2048 ports)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delete various macOS and Windows-related files from the source code (no longer relevant)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark JACK-Session as deprecated, please use NSM instead&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove unnecessary GPL include from LGPL code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Split example-clients and tools, as done in JACK1 many years ago (WIP)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write Windows registry key during installation, so 3rd parties can find jackd.exe (as HKLM\Software\JACK\Location)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;jack_control: Fix handling of dbus bytes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;jack_control: Return a proper exit status on DBus exception&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;jack_property: Fix possible crash with &amp;quot;-l&amp;quot; argument usage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;jack_wait: Add client name option -n/--name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix compilation of documentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix compilation of mixed mode with meta-data enabled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix compilation with mingw&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix client-side crash if initial meta-data DB setup fails&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix macOS semaphore usage, so it works again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several fixes for Windows (with contributions from Kjetil S. Matheussen)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several minor fixes and grammar corrections (with contributions from Adam Miartus and Timo Wischer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release is a nice good step towards what was planned back in 2017 with the v1.9.12 release.&lt;br/&gt;
JACK1 remains in bug-fix mode, while JACK2 is slowly incorporating changes from it.&lt;br/&gt;
The examples and tools directory was split in the same way that JACK1 is,
so that in the future we can use those as submodules instead of having duplicated code between JACK versions.&lt;br/&gt;
Once we have matching headers, examples and tools we can begin the switch.&lt;br/&gt;
If you are reading this and want to help, pull requests for syncing those repositories code to what JACK2 has will be greatly appreciated!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those that missed it, JACK-Session has been marked as deprecated. Please use &amp;quot;New Session Manager&amp;quot; instead.&lt;br/&gt;
You can find more about the project &lt;a href=&quot;https://linuxaudio.github.io/new-session-manager/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
This includes links to the source code, bug/issue tracker and documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the future, short-term plan is to continue the feature parity between JACK1 and JACK2.&lt;br/&gt;
We are pretty much there now besides JACK2 missing the a2jmidi and zita internal clients (and the special options to use them).&lt;br/&gt;
Support for macOS arm64 is in progress, and there is a whole range of pull requests and issues to investigate and fix.&lt;br/&gt;
Focus will be on those before any features are even thought of, unless they serve to improve something.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>JACK2 v1.9.13 release</title>
        <author><name>falkTX</name></author>
        <link href="https://jackaudio.org/jackaudio.github.com/news/2019/10/06/jack2-v1.9.13-release/"/>
        <published>2019-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <id>/jackaudio.github.com/news/2019/10/06/jack2-v1.9.13-release/</id>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new version of JACK2 has just been released.&lt;br/&gt;
You can grab the latest release source code at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&quot;&gt;https://github.com/jackaudio/jack2/releases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official changelog is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meta-data API implementation. (and a few tools updated with support for it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Correct GPL licence to LGPL for files needed to build libjack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove FreeBoB backend (superseded by FFADO).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;define JACK_LIB_EXPORT, useful for internal clients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark jack_midi_reset_buffer as deprecated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add example systemd unit file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Signal to systemd when jackd is ready.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set &amp;quot;seq&amp;quot; alsa midi driver to maximum resolution possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix loading internal clients from another internal client.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code cleanup and various fixes. (too many to mention here, see git log for details)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release is focused on meta-data support, and this is why it took so long.&lt;br/&gt;
There might be odd cases here and there and a few bugs, as it is often the case
for all software...&lt;br/&gt;
So please make sure to report back any issues!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks goes to Rui Nuno Capela for the initial pull-request regarding
meta-data.&lt;br/&gt;
There was some work needed afterwards, but that was the biggest hurdle and
motivation needed for a new release. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still no updated macOS or Windows builds, those will be handled at
a later date.&lt;br/&gt;
Current plan is to have JACK1 feature-parity first
(only a2jmidid and zita internal clients missing now),&lt;br/&gt;
and afterwards merging examples/tools and header files to be shared between
JACK1 and JACK2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation regarding development of JACK and JACK1 considered legacy has not
changed since last release 2 years ago.&lt;br/&gt;
See &lt;a href=&quot;/news/2017/12/21/jack2-v1-9-12-release-and-future-plans.html&quot;&gt;JACK2 v1.9.12 release and future plans&lt;/a&gt; post for more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: I will be in Cologne for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sonoj.org/&quot;&gt;Sonoj&lt;/a&gt;, giving a talk about
&amp;quot;Past, Present and Future of JACK&amp;quot;.&lt;br/&gt;
There is no registration fee, so please feel free to come by and say hello! :)&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </entry>
</feed>
